Alok Khandai

Operational Analyst (SQL DBA) Engineer - UNISYS

Bengaluru, Karnataka - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Alok-Khandai/5be849e443b8f467

Having 3.5 Years of IT experience in SQL Database Administration, System Analysis, Design,

Development & Support of MS SQL Servers in Production, Development environments &

Replication and Cluster Server Environments.

Working Experience with relational database such as SQL.

Experience in Installation, Configuration, Maintenance and Administration of SQL Server.

Experience in upgrading SQL Server.

Good experience with implementing DR solution, High Availability of database servers using

Database mirroring and replications and Log Shipping.

Experience in implementing SQL Server security and Object permissions like maintaining

Database authentication modes, creation of users, configuring permissions and assigning roles

to users.

Experience in creating Jobs, Alerts, SQL Mail Agent

Experience in performing integrity checks. Methods include configuring the database

maintenance plan wizard and DBCC utilities

Experience in using Performance Monitor, SQL Profiler and optimizing the queries, tracing long

running queries and deadlocks.

Experience in applying patches and service packs to keep the database at current patch level.

Ability to manage own work and multitask to meet tight deadlines without losing sight of

priorities..

Willing to relocate to: Bengaluru, Karnataka

WORK EXPERIENCE

Operational Analyst (SQL DBA) Engineer

UNISYS - Bengaluru, Karnataka -

July 2016 to Present

Having 3.5 Years of IT experience in SQL Database Administration, System Analysis, Design,

Development & Support of MS SQL Servers in Production, Development environments &

Replication and Cluster Server Environments.

- Working Experience with relational database such as SQL.
- Experience in Installation, Configuration, Maintenance and Administration of SQL Server.
- Experience in upgrading SQL Server.
- Good experience with implementing DR solution, High Availability of database servers using Database mirroring and replications and Log Shipping.
- Experience in implementing SQL Server security and Object permissions like maintaining Database authentication modes, creation of users, configuring permissions and assigning roles to users.

DBA Support Analyst

Microsoft Corporation - Redmond, WA -

https://www.indeed.com/r/Alok-Khandai/5be849e443b8f467?isid=rex-download&ikw=download-top&co=IN

July 2016 to Present

Client Description:

Microsoft Corporation is an American public multinational corporation headquartered in Redmond, Washington, USA that develops, manufactures, licenses, and supports a wide range of products and services predominantly related to computing through its various product divisions.

Environment:

Microsoft has E2E development and production environment of more than 25000 servers and applications. We are responsible for pro-active monitoring of all the servers and their jobs using monitoring tools to reduce critical business impact by alerting respective peer teams. Microsoft Service Enterprise an ITSM tools are used for ticketing and SharePoint portal is used to store all technical and process documentation.

Roles and Responsibilities:

Responsible for Database support, troubleshooting, planning and migration. Resource planning
and coordination for application migrations with project managers, application and web app
teams. Project involved guidance and adherence to standardized procedures for planned data
center consolidation for worldwide centers using in-house corporate and third party applications
based on SQL 2000 in upgrade project to SQL 2005.

· Monitoring of database size and disk space in Production, Staging & Development environments

Performed installation of SQL Enterprise 2005 64bit version on Windows 2003 servers on

Enterprise systems of clustered and standalone servers in enterprise Data Centers. Patch

applications.

Failover cluster testing and resolution on HP servers as well as monitoring and backup reporting

setup with Microsoft Operations Manager and backup teams.

Working in Microsoft production environment which includes applications and servers.

• Configured Transactional Replication and Log Shipping with SQL Server Management Studio as

well as basic account management and troubleshooting with connectivity, security and firewall

issues.

• Handling issues related to Server Availability, Performance.

Performed Production support and on Call duties

• Conducted Performance Tuning using SQL Profiler and Windows Performance Monitor.

Worked with various business groups while developing their applications, assisting in database

design, installing SQL Server clients, phasing from development to QA and to Production

environment.

Previous Project

Project Title: Finance Support

Client: Costco Wholesale Corporation (USA)

Team size: 22

Role: DBA Support Analyst

Environment: Window 10

(SQL DBA Analyst) Engineer

HCL Technologies - Bengaluru, Karnataka -

November 2014 to July 2016

= Performed server installation and configurations for SQL Server 2005 and SQL Server 2000.

= Performed installation of SQL Server Service Packs

= Upgraded databases from SQL Server 2000 to SQL Server 2005.

= Scheduled Full and Transactional log backups for the user created and system databases in

the production environment using the Database Maintenance Plan Wizard.

- **=** Setup backup and restoration jobs for development and QA environments
- = Created transactional replication for the reporting applications.
- = Implemented disaster recovery solution at the remote site for the production databases using Log Shipping.
- = Used System monitor to find the bottlenecks in CPU, Disk I/O and memory devices and improved the database server performance.
- = Used SQL Server Profiler to monitor and record database activities of particular users and applications.
- Used DBCC commands to troubleshoot issues related to database consistency
- = Worked with various business groups while developing their applications, assisting in database design, installing SQL Server clients, phasing from development to QA and to Production environment

Microsoft Corporation -

November 2014 to July 2016

Client Description:

- ❖ Costco Wholesale Corporation operates an international chain of membership warehouses, mainly under the "Costco Wholesale" name, that carry quality, brand name merchandise at substantially lower prices than are typically found at conventional wholesale or retail sources. The warehouses are designed to help small-to-medium-sized businesses reduce costs in purchasing for resale and for everyday business use. Individuals may also purchase for their personal needs.
- Responsibilities:
- > Performed server installation and configurations for SQL Server 2005 and SQL Server 2000.
- ➤ Performed installation of SQL Server Service Packs
- ➤ Upgraded databases from SQL Server 2000 to SQL Server 2005.
- > Scheduled Full and Transactional log backups for the user created and system databases in the production environment using the Database Maintenance Plan Wizard.
- > Setup backup and restoration jobs for development and QA environments
- > Created transactional replication for the reporting applications.
- > Implemented disaster recovery solution at the remote site for the production databases using Log Shipping.

➤ Used System monitor to find the bottlenecks in CPU, Disk I/O and memory devices and improved

the database server performance.

> Used SQL Server Profiler to monitor and record database activities of particular users and

applications.

> Used DBCC commands to troubleshoot issues related to database consistency

➤ Worked with various business groups while developing their applications, assisting in database

design, installing SQL Server clients, phasing from development to QA and to Production

environment

EDUCATION

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering in CSE

Indira Gandhi Institute Of Technology

2012

SKILLS

Database (3 years), SQL (3 years), Sql Dba

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

TECHNICAL PROFICIENCY

Operating Environment: [...] Windows95/98/XP/NT

Database Tool: SQL Management Studio (MSSQL), Business

Development Studio, Visual studio 2005

❖ Database Language: SQL, PL/SQL

❖ Ticket Tracking Tool: Service Now

Reporting Tools: MS Reporting Services, SAS

❖ Languages: C, C++, PL/SQL